prodigygame.com 2017-06-07

# Prodigy Math Game

In delivering on Prodigy's mission to foster a love of learning in children worldwide, we are committed to protecting the privacy of our users and providing a safe, online environment for students, educators, and parents to collaborate and advance learning. 

This Privacy Policy outlines what information we collect and why we collect it, how this information is used and shared, and what your options are regarding your personal information (accessing, updating and deleting your information). 

In our commitment to protect the privacy of children, Prodigy participates in the iKeepSafe Safe Harbor program. Prodigy has been granted the iKeepSafe Privacy California Student Badge, signifying that our products have been reviewed and approved for having policies and practices surrounding the collection, use, maintenance and disclosure of personal information from children consistent with each of the following program guidelines. 

  * The Children's Online Privacy Protection Act [(COPPA)](https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/rules/rulemaking-regulatory-reform-proceedings/childrens-online-privacy-protection-rule)
  * The Family Education Rights and Protection Act [(FERPA)](http://www2.ed.gov/policy/gen/guid/fpco/ferpa/index.html)
  * The California Student Privacy Act [(link)](https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=201320140SB1177)
  * Collection of Student Information from Social Media (California Education Code 49073.6 Pupil Records: Social Media)
  * California AB 1584 - Privacy of Pupil Records: 3rd-Party Digital Storage & Education Software (California Education Code section 49073.1)
  * The Protection of Pupil Rights Amendment [(PPRA)](http://familypolicy.ed.gov/ppra)
  * The Student Online Personal Information Protection Act [(SOPIPA)](https://www.commonsensemedia.org/kids-action/our-issues/a-positive-media-and-technology-world/sopipa)
  * The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act [(HIPAA)](https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-professionals/privacy/laws-regulations/) of 1996

This Privacy Policy applies to all products and services provided by SMARTeacher Inc. (hereinafter called "Prodigy", "we", "us", or "our").

Last Modified Date: November 22, 2016

## Table of Contents

  1. What is Prodigy and who uses it?
  2. What information does Prodigy collect and why?
  3. How does Prodigy protect and secure my information?
  4. What student information is visible to others within Prodigy’s virtual world?
  5. Does Prodigy share data with third parties?
  6. Parental Choices
  7. Automatically Collected Information
  8. How can I view, modify, or delete my information?
  9. How will Prodigy notify me of changes to this Privacy Policy?
  10. How can I contact Prodigy with privacy questions?
  11. How Prodigy maintains FERPA compliance
  12. How Prodigy maintains COPPA compliance

## Overview

Personally Identifiable Information (PII) is any information you provide to us that personally identifies you, like your name or email address, or other information which could be reasonably linked to such identifying information by us. We will only collect, use, and share your personal information in accordance with this Privacy Policy. 

## 1\. What is Prodigy and who uses it?

Prodigy is an online math game and education platform that is used by millions of students, parents, and teachers across the world. 

Students log in to Prodigy's online game to play and learn math. Within Prodigy, students get to design their own wizard avatar and explore a massive online world. They encounter monsters and engage in ‘math battles', where they must answer curriculum-aligned math questions in order to defeat their opponent. As students play, Prodigy is constantly adapting the educational content that they encounter, so that each student advances through the curriculum and succeeds at their own pace. 

Educators such as teachers and school/district administrators use Prodigy to engage and assess their students. While Prodigy is not intended to be used as a sole assessment tool, there are built-in features that simplify the assessment process through analyzing performance data that is aligned with the curriculum. As students play, teachers are able to access real-time reports on how many questions their students are answering, which expectations/standards they've covered, and where they are having difficulty. Teachers can also create custom ‘assignments' or ‘plans' to better align Prodigy to their lesson plan and assess students on specific topics or skills. 

Parents use Prodigy to engage, assess, and allow their children an opportunity for differentiated math practice. As children play, parents are able to access real-time reports on how many questions their child is answering, which expectations/standards they've covered, and where they are having difficulty. Parents can also create custom ‘assignments' or ‘plans' to cater the math content that their child is working on in the game. 

## 2\. What information does Prodigy collect and why?

Prodigy collects information in a number of different ways in order to provide a completely personalized education experience for each child, and to provide real-time reporting and assessment features to teachers and parents. 

Prodigy has been certified by [iKeepSafe](http://ikeepsafe.org/), an FTC-approved COPPA Safe Harbor, for compliance with their COPPA Safe Harbor program. We do not ask for or require children to provide personal information beyond that which is reasonably necessary to use Prodigy. Information collected from students is never used or disclosed for third-party advertising or any kind of behaviorally-targeted advertising, and it is never sold or rented to anyone, including marketers or advertisers. 

## If a student is registering to play Prodigy

Prodigy collects the minimum amount of information from students to allow for a personalized educational experience and to facilitate progress monitoring for parents and teachers. 

There are two ways a student can be signed up for Prodigy: through their parent/teacher's account, or independently through the game. 

When students are signed up for the game through a parent or teacher's account the parent/teacher is asked to enter the student's name (first name and last name or last initial), and Prodigy asks the student for: 

  * A fictional avatar name that students can select from a pre-specified list of options (e.g. Billy Summerwalker)
  * Fictional avatar appearance

When students sign up directly through the game with a teacher's class code (an alphanumeric code that is unique to a teacher's account) or parent's email address, Prodigy asks for: 

  * First name
  * Last name initial
  * Password
  * Location including State/Province and/or Country (e.g. Ontario, Other Canadian Province, Texas, Florida, Other US State, or Other Country)
  * Grade
  * Parent's email address
  * A fictional avatar name that students can select from a pre-specified list of options (e.g. Billy Summerwalker)
  * Fictional avatar appearance

Prodigy automatically generates a unique username based on the student's first name, last initial, and a number (e.g. AlexP57). Since students are asked to only enter their initial for their last name (without a linked parent/teacher account), Prodigy does not have PII for these students.

The student's name is used to identify that student to their parent or teacher so that they are able to effectively differentiate instruction. The student's grade and location are used to place them in the most appropriate curriculum (e.g. Common Core Math Standards) and grade level. The student's username and password are used to allow them to securely log in to Prodigy's game via Prodigy's website. The student's fictional avatar name is used to display their avatar online to other players, while keeping their real name and identity hidden. The student's parent's email address is used to inform parents that their child has registered for an account on Prodigy.

As students play, Prodigy collects information on the game features they interact with, math skills they encounter, and questions they answer (hereinafter referred to as "Performance Data"). Prodigy uses a student's Performance Data to customize their educational experience, including finding an optimal path through Prodigy's math curriculum.

Performance Data from one or more students may also be aggregated and used by Prodigy to improve Prodigy's educational algorithms.

Select components of a student's Performance Data are reported back to a student's parent and/or teacher, in order to allow the parent/teacher to monitor the student's progress and customize the student's educational experience.

In addition to the information entered by the student, Prodigy automatically collects some information from any use of our Service as set forth in the "Automatically Collected Information" section.

If a student is signed up through a teacher account, the school remains in control of the student's Personally Identifiable Information.

## If a parent is registering to play Prodigy

When parents sign up for a free account on Prodigy, Prodigy asks for:

  * Full name
  * Email address
  * Password
  * Curriculum (e.g., Ontario Math Curriculum)

A parent's name, email address, and password are used for identification purposes and to allow the parent to securely log in to Prodigy's parent dashboard. Email addresses are also used to communicate important information about the parent's account via email. A parent's choice of curriculum allows Prodigy to report progress against the most appropriate list of standards or expectations.

Parents who sign up for a paid membership to Prodigy are asked for their child's username, child's password, credit card number, postal/zip code, card expiration date, and Card Verification Code (CVC), in addition to all of the information required for a free parent account (listed in the paragraph above). This information is used by Prodigy to apply the appropriate charges to the parent's credit card, and to ensure that the membership is applied to the correct student account. Prodigy does NOT directly store any credit card information - all credit card information and transactions are stored by our payment provider, [Stripe](https://stripe.com/). Please [click here](https://stripe.com/docs/security) for more information about how Stripe secures customer information.

In addition, Prodigy automatically collects some information from any use of our Service as set forth in the "Automatically Collected Information" section.

## If a teacher is registering to play Prodigy

When teachers sign up for a free account on Prodigy, Prodigy asks for:

  * Full name
  * Email address
  * Password
  * Grade
  * Curriculum (e.g. Common Core Math Standards)
  * District/board
  * School

A teacher's name, email address, and password are used for identification purposes and to allow the teacher to securely log in to Prodigy's teacher dashboard. Email addresses are also used to communicate important information about the teacher's account via email. A teacher's choice of curriculum allows Prodigy to report progress against the most appropriate list of standards or expectations.

In addition, Prodigy automatically collects some information from any use of our Service as set forth in the "Automatically Collected Information" section.

## School/District Administrators

Prodigy collects all of the information required for a free teacher account from school/district administrators, in addition to a list of the specific schools within the district that the administrator works with. For security purposes, Prodigy also reserves the right to verify a school administrator's identity via email, telephone, or another method that we deem appropriate.

## 3\. How does Prodigy protect and secure my information?

Protecting your information is extremely important to us. In addition to annual staff training to ensure the security and confidentiality of student records, we take several precautions to ensure that user information is secure:

**Password protection** \- Secure passwords are the first line of defense for your student, parent, teacher, or school/district administrator account. In order to prevent unauthorized access to your account, we recommend choosing a password that is memorable but hard to guess, and keeping your password confidential at all times. Additional information on password safety is available on the [Government of Canada's website](http://www.getcybersafe.gc.ca/cnt/prtct-yrslf/prtctn-dntty/usng-psswrds-eng.aspx), the [US Department of Homeland Security's website](https://www.us-cert.gov/ncas/tips/ST04-002), and at [ConnectSafely.org](http://www.connectsafely.org/tips-to-create-and-manage-strong-passwords/).

**SSL encryption** \- Prodigy protects any information transferred through our website by encrypting it with the Secure Socket Layer (SSL) protocol by default. This makes it more difficult for malicious third parties to intercept your information.

**Salted hashing** \- Passwords and other sensitive information are never stored in plain text, and are instead protected via salted hashes.

**Independent service-level APIs** \- Students' PII is only available through a select few APIs. This minimizes the impact of a potential breach of any individual API.

**Database protection** \- Prodigy's databases are inaccessible to all IP addresses except for a pre-specified list of whitelisted IP addresses. All databases are also password protected.

**Periodic data review** \- Our team periodically reviews our data collection, storage, and processing policies and practices against leading industry standards to ensure that we are compliant.

While we do our best to keep your data secure, Prodigy cannot guarantee the security of your data. Several factors including, but not limited to, hardware/software failure, outages, human error, attacks, or unauthorized use may compromise the security of our users' information. In the case of a data security breach, we will do our best to alert any affected users electronically via our website, the email account you have provided, and/or another medium that we deem appropriate, depending on the magnitude and severity of the breach.

Prodigy maintains computerized data that includes personal information that Prodigy does not own. Should a breach occur, Prodigy will notify the account owner of the breach of the security of the data immediately following discovery, if the personal information was, or is reasonably believed to have been, acquired by an unauthorized person. 

The security breach notification will be written in plain language and will be titled "Notice of Data Breach." The breach notification will include the following information:

  * What happened
  * What information was involved
  * What we are doing about the breach
  * What you can do
  * Contact information

## 4\. What student information is visible to others within Prodigy's virtual world?

Since Prodigy is an online multiplayer game, students are able to interact with other players within our virtual world. However, we do take several precautions to ensure that any Personally Identifiable Information (PII) is only visible to an authorized parent and/or teacher within their password-protected Prodigy account, and is not available to the public or other players within Prodigy's virtual world.

Information that is visible to other players within Prodigy's virtual world includes:

**Avatar names** \- Students get to choose a name for their wizard avatar from a pre-specified list (e.g. Alex Fairydancer). This avatar name is displayed to others in the Prodigy world, in order to protect the student's real name.

**Avatar profiles** \- A student's avatar's appearance, clothing, items, and key game statistics (e.g. level, hearts, stars, gold, etc.) are available for other players to view in the game. This does not include any of the student's personal information.

**Student usernames** \- To discourage students from using their full name or other personal information, student usernames are generated based on a combination of their first name, last initial, and a number (e.g. AlexP123). Student usernames are only visible to the respective student and their parent/teacher.

**Safe chat messages** \- Students have the ability to send safe chat messages to others within Prodigy's virtual world. These messages can only be selected from a pre-specified list of phrases (e.g. "I like your outfit"), and hence, students are not able to disclose personal information such as their telephone number or address. This also prevents students from sending offensive or inappropriate messages.

As a website trusted by millions of educators, parents, and students worldwide, Prodigy is committed to never selling or leasing your or your students' personal information with third parties.

Prior to engaging into a relationship with a third-party service provider, Prodigy will first review their privacy policies and ensure that these are compliant with those regulations that Prodigy is adhering to and that they are aware that Prodigy is directed to children. Third-party service providers will have their privacy policies reviewed by Prodigy on an annual basis to ensure that any changes made do not affect compliance with all applicable legislations. Please visit our support website for a [complete list of our service providers](https://prodigygame.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/217076826).

We value your privacy, and hence restrict sharing your data with third parties, with the exception of the following circumstances:

**Other users that have invited you to Prodigy** \- As a teacher or parent, if you are invited to create an account on Prodigy by another teacher or parent on Prodigy, we will let them know if you have created an account, and the number of Active Students linked to your account. Active Students are students that have answered at least 20 questions within Prodigy.

**School/District Administrators** \- Verified school/district administrators (e.g. your student's Principal or Superintendent) who have created accounts on Prodigy may be able to see your and your students' names, activity, and Performance Data on Prodigy.

**Third-party integrations on Prodigy** \- When you use third-party apps, websites, or services to log into (e.g. using your Google Classroom to log in to your teacher account) or share information from Prodigy (e.g. sending out a tweet on the number of questions answered in your class), they may receive information on your activity on Prodigy and/or what you share. Information collected by third-party integrations is subject to the third party's own terms and privacy policy.

**Service providers** \- Prodigy uses various vendors, partners, and service providers to help us deliver our services to our users. For example, we use a mail service called [Sparkpost](https://www.sparkpost.com/) to deliver emails to our users on our behalf, as it would take a lot of resources for us to develop our own email delivery platform. As a result, some of your information, including Personally Identifiable Information, may be shared with our service providers in order for them to perform their tasks. Wherever possible, we ensure that we only share the minimal amount of information for the respective service provider to perform their service. We carefully vet all of our service providers and ensure that they protect and secure your information in a way that is consistent with this Privacy Policy. Please see a [complete list of third-party service providers here](https://prodigygame.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/217076826).

**Analytics services** \- Prodigy uses third-party analytics services to better understand how our users are interacting with our product, and to improve our product over time. For example, we use a video tracking software called [Vidyard](https://vidyard.com/) to track which one of our tutorial videos is being clicked on most frequently and how our users are interacting with these videos. In this process, some of your personal information, Performance Data, and interactions with our product may be collected by or shared with these analytics services in order for them to perform their service. We carefully vet all of our analytics services and ensure that they protect and secure your information in a way that is consistent with this Privacy Policy. Please see a [complete list of third-party analytics services here](https://prodigygame.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/217076826).

**Non-personally identifiable information** \- Prodigy may share aggregated, non-personally identifiable information with the public for marketing or other purposes. For example, we may share data on the percentage of students on Prodigy who use the game both at home and in school in our marketing materials to parents. None of this information will contain any Personally Identifiable Information about individual users.

**Legal requirements** \- Prodigy may share our users' information if we are legally obligated to do so to comply with the law. In these cases, we will disclose only the information that is deemed a legal necessity by the applicable law, so as to protect the rights and safety of our users.

**Change of control** \- In the case that Prodigy is acquired or merges with a third party, your data will still be protected as per the terms outlined in this Privacy Policy. In the case that Prodigy goes out of business or files for bankruptcy, we will protect your personal information, and will not sell it to any third party.

**Consent** \- Prodigy reserves the right to share your or your students' information with your explicit consent, given verbally, on paper, or electronically. For example, we may publish a case study with a teacher's name, school, district, and the number of questions her students have answered on Prodigy with her explicit consent.

## 6\. Parental Choices

We understand that as a parent or legal guardian of a child, controlling your child's information and access to online resources can be difficult. In accordance with COPPA, if a child signs up for a Prodigy account independently, we require the child to enter a parent's email address so that an email can be sent to their parent seeking the parent's consent for the child to engage with our services.

While we do our best to protect your child's information and provide them with an awesome educational experience, legal parents or guardians do have the right to request that their child's account be deleted by contacting us. In order to do so, we may require verification of the parent or guardian's identity, and verification that they are the legal parent and/or guardian of that child. Please keep in mind that this will also prohibit your child from using their Prodigy account in class, and that they may miss out on class work or homework if their teacher uses Prodigy as part of their math strategy.

## 7\. Automatically Collected Information

In addition to information that you provide, Prodigy (and our Service Providers or Analytics Services) may also collect certain information automatically while you are engaging with our Service in order to track trends, help us to improve our service, and provide a more customized experience to our users.

For example, we automatically track your approximate location to provide you with information on the most relevant math curriculum/standards in your state/country. A user viewing our website from Ontario, Canada would get information on the Ontario Math Curriculum, while a user from Texas, USA, would get information from the Texas Essential Knowledge and Skills (TEKS) standards.

This automatically collected information includes but is not limited to: device information, location information, session information, browser information, and cookies and similar technologies.

## 8\. How can I view, modify, or delete my information?

As a parent, teacher, or school/district administrator, you can view and/or modify your information through your password-protected Prodigy account. Your Prodigy account also allows you to view and/or modify information for your child(ren) and student(s).

As a parent, teacher or school district, you have the ability to contact us at any time to review Personally Identifiable Information and categories of data being held in education records. 

Your Prodigy account may limit you from modifying certain information (e.g. the username that you use to log in to your teacher or parent account), and in these cases, we suggest contacting us, as we may be able to modify the information on your behalf.

While we would be sad to see you go, you are able to request to delete your account at any time by writing to us. You are also able to request to delete your child/student's account as long as you have a parent or teacher account that is linked to that child. In this event, we will delete your and/or your child's personal information from our systems, and will remove access from the account within 10 business days of your request.

Please send your written request to: support@prodigygame.com or mail it in to: 1100 Burloak Drive, Suite 200, Burlington, ON, L7L 6B2 or call us at 1 866 585 4655.

## 9\. How will Prodigy notify me of changes to this Privacy Policy?

We are committed to keeping your data private and secure, and as technology, privacy laws, and best practices evolve over time, we will do our best to keep this Privacy Policy up-to-date.

For minor changes which do not reduce your rights under this Privacy Policy, we will notify our users via our website and/or directly by email (using the email address provided). For more major changes, we will notify our users directly by email (using the email address provided).

Schools signed up for a membership will be notified in advance of any material changes to privacy policies, including practices around new or additional data collection, or practices that may lessen the previously noted protections around student-data privacy.

We encourage all users to review this Privacy Policy from time to time and write to us with any questions or concerns. If you do not agree with any updates, you have the option of terminating your account and discontinuing your use of our services. However, by continuing to use our services after a change to this Privacy Policy, you are agreeing to accept the changes and the terms of the updated Privacy Policy in their entirety.

If you have any questions or concerns about our Privacy Policy, please contact our support team at: support@prodigygame.com or mail it in to: 1100 Burloak Drive, Suite 200, Burlington, ON, L7L 6B2 or call us at 1 866 585 4655.

## 11\. How does Prodigy maintain FERPA compliance?

FERPA is "The Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act". It protects the privacy of students' "Educational Records" by specifying how and with whom schools can share information from these records.

Prodigy has been granted the iKeepSafe California Student Privacy Badge, which validates our compliance with FERPA. Please refer to this [support article](https://prodigygame.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/217991063) for more details.

## 12\. How does Prodigy maintain COPPA compliance?

The Children's Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA) is a Federal Trade Commission (FTC) Rule designed to ensure that parents remain in control of personal information collected from their young children online.

Prodigy has been granted the iKeepSafe California Student Privacy Badge, which validates our compliance with COPPA. Please refer to this [support article](https://prodigygame.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/217075546) for more details.

iKeepSafe is a FTC-approved COPPA Safe Harbor Organization. For information on how consumers can ask questions or file complaints related to Prodigy's Privacy Policy and practices, please email COPPAPrivacy@ikeepsafe.org.
